[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software welcome listeners to a
new show of uranium I'm here with Linda
rising Linda rising is an independent
consultant from Nashville Tennessee in
the USA and I just learned that she is
turning as 73 tomorrow yes st. Patrick's
Day that's my birthday
very very good so her special duties are
patterns retrospectives agile processes
organizational change and how the brain
works she has a PhD in computer science
which she earned one months before the
fiftieth birthday so 23 years ago yeah
she has been previously a chemist and
has four books I learned no five books
published to about three about design
patterns and the more recent ones are
fearless change and more fearless change
and she talks of herself as an informed
layperson of cognitive neuroscience yes
I don't have any degrees and in that
field alright anything you would like to
add I'm also a musician I in fact I
think there are a lot of people who are
computer scientists or mathematicians
who are also musical and I direct four
groups recorder players in our
retirement community my husband just
retired so that's why we moved to
nashville tennessee and we lived and we
live in a retirement community where we
have a lot of interesting other people
to study very nice yeah so you have
already been on two shows on a surrender
which is show 105 on retrospectives
which is actually
the show which reduced me to
retrospective and thereby changed my
life my banking and her book fearless
changed the first one has been the topic
of episode 193 ah sorry 49 once it's
really nice and actually we should
mention that we are recording the show
during a scarf and which is a very nice
conference in Poland and the organizers
of this conference were so nice to
provide us with this room so you have a
quiet room for this recording yeah
where's that Jeanne said I think we
could start our show before starting I
would like to mention that you can of
course comment to that show on the
website se reggienet or you can email us
team at SU AUD Twitter LinkedIn Facebook
Google+ we are on all of them please let
us know what you think of this show or
any other show feedback is really
important to us so Linda we want to talk
about something I called the edge hi
brain sounds like a good thing yeah
sounds like it
so I know you start your talks with a
disclaimer why is that saying well it
started as a joke because I feel that
I'm talking outside my area of certified
expertise and even though I've been
doing it now for almost 20 years I don't
have any degrees in psychology or
cognitive neuroscience but that's my
primary interest and I try to connect
everything with the latest research in
neuroscience and I do that for a number
of reasons one because there is a lot of
research in cognitive neuroscience and
it's very difficult for people who don't
have as much time as I do to keep up
with it and I think it's important for
people in software development to learn
as much as they can because they don't
do their own experiments that was the
talk this morning so one
the things we can do is look at what
other people are doing so I try to do
that I try to read as much as I can I
try to filter what's out there I try to
make what I think is important
applicable to software so maybe let's
take a step back then you haven't
studied neurosciences but why did you
become interested in them well when you
look at all of the degrees you mentioned
the PhD and what I don't usually put on
the resume are all the degrees that I
have or some that I didn't quite finish
I finished the PhD two masters degrees
and a bachelor's degree but I have
almost another bachelor's degree and
another master's degree and another PhD
I just didn't finish them but when you
look at the topics for all those they're
all technical they're computer science
or math or chemistry and I did take one
psychology course for my bachelor's
degree it was a requirement that's the
only official course I've ever had
that's connected to psychology or
cognitive neuroscience and I didn't like
it what didn't you like it because it
seemed too fuzzy and the the experiments
were all to do with things that I didn't
really care about and I didn't think
they were very interesting but now if
you look at the experiments in
neuroscience they're much more technical
the equipment the technology that's
involved in these experiments is
overwhelming they can slide people in an
MRI machine and they can watch parts of
their brain light up when they look at a
can of coca-cola and they can see more
than you know what you really like and
what you don't really like so that
research is I think much more
interesting than it was say 50 years ago
so it has become a more technical yes it
has
and therefore I think more interesting
and the topics are I think as a result
of that more interesting because they
can dig deeper they know more about how
the brain works and since all of that
research is now available to us we can
see more direct applications it's more
useful like for example well we know for
instance that people cannot multitask
and you can actually show that in
experiments and what we believe about
ourselves is that we can look at our
email and we can also listen to music
and we can try to code something and we
can overhear what's going on in the next
cubicle and we can also make notes about
other ideas that pop up we're trying to
do for some of us maybe six or eight
things all at the same time then the
research is pretty clear it asks
impossible
yeah I have to say I noticed that when I
do an interview and want to make a note
on the next session at the same time
photos on what they what the guest you
say you can't do it I remember reading
one research study where they said the
analogy or the metaphor here is try to
sing two songs at the same time you
can't do it you can do it unless you go
back and forth
so we're linear processors or at least
our conscious minds are and so once
where the research is pretty clear then
maybe it behooves us not to try to text
while we drive we know that our
attention is distracted we know that
it's not a safe thing to do we know
we're putting our own lives at risk so a
lot of that is directly applicable we do
a better job of thinking if we are
focused on one thing at a time but
having said that we also the research
also shows that we're very good if we
don't focus too long which is another
thing we tend to do we tend to focus on
one thing for an extremely long period
of time and what we should do is give it
up
move on to something else and then when
we do that immediately we think of
something that will help us solve your
you've probably seen that yeah
like when when you then you're too deep
in the rabbit hole and confluence
solution yes you get it when you when
you get the coffee not when you're
that's right digging deeper yes that's
right stand up go get a cup of coffee
and all of a sudden bingo there it is
so getting up and leaving it is very
effective yeah all right so you have a
talk called the edge on mindset in which
you align or describe a fixed mindset
and an agile mindset
can you explain what this agile and
fixed mindset is about so that talk is
available online of given versions of it
many times the first time was at as the
closing keynote at the u.s. agile
conference in 2011 and it was really
surprising to me because right up to the
time I gave the talk I kept thinking oh
this is kind of a silly topic no one
will really like it it will be one of
those weird talks and I will give it
once and I saw that you you actually
said I'm always the one who has to give
the workshop weird because I I think I
have wide-ranging interests and I do
find strange connections well sometimes
they work out sometimes they don't work
out and I remember thinking oh well it's
the closing keynote nobody's here
everybody's gone home nobody stays for
the closing keynote and that result of
that keynote has been so surprising to
me because it's definitely the most
popular one I'm still giving it this is
now 2015 I was still giving that talk I
almost don't want to list it when I talk
to somebody about topics
I think nah we don't include that again
but if I don't then they'll ask for it
that's the one we want we want the agile
mindset so it's very surprising
it has to do with research about people
who believe one thing or another about
intelligence the people who have the
fixed mindset believe that you're born
with the intelligence that you have and
there's nothing you can do to change
that you have what you have you have it
or you don't those who have the agile
mindset on the other hand say well of
course you're limited by what you have
we know not everyone is going to be a
genius we know that you're not going to
be Beethoven or Einstein I don't care
how much you work but I believe that you
can be better you could be better
tomorrow than you are today if you're
determined and if you work at it you can
be better so you can always make some
improvement so the difference in those
two mindsets turns out to be profound it
affects everything that we do and of
course for me the immediate connection
when I read the research was well the
it's called the growth mindset in the
research papers the growth mindset is
agile that's exactly what the agile
mindset says is that we don't know what
we are today but we know tomorrow will
produce something and we'll learn
something we may fail we may succeed but
we're gonna learn and it's about
learning it's about improving it's about
getting better that is the growth
mindset or now I call that the agile
mindset yeah so the research you
mentioned this was done by by Carol
Dweck yes Carol Dweck and now many of
her graduate students have done
follow-on work to say well what can we
do with people who have a fixed mindset
can we change whether they're children
whether they're adults and so there's a
lot of follow-on research now beyond
what she did she's still working she
teaches at Stanford University and she
has a she has written a
accessible book written a book called
mindset yeah and it's it does cover the
research so it's research oriented but
it is a book that anyone can read and
there are other people who have picked
up on it Malcolm Gladwell wrote an
article in The New Yorker magazine
that's also of course very accessible
Gladwell's and a wonderful writer and he
sort of built an article beginning with
her research Poe Bronson wrote a book on
nature or nurture for parents and
there's an article that he wrote for New
Yorker magazine called what not to tell
your children mm-hmm so all parents
should read that and it's based on the
research that Carol Dweck did yeah so to
give me a more clear example so can you
describe how people with different
mindsets react in common situations well
if we look at some differences between
and I'm gonna use the term agile even
though that's not your research term
between fixed and agile we know the main
difference or the primary difference is
the belief in intelligence or talent or
ability those are the fixed mindset
believe you have what you have and
there's nothing you can do about it you
have it where you don't those with the
agile mindset believe yes of course
you're limited but you can always get
better so once you have those two
mindsets that effects first of all the
kinds of goals you have in life so for
those with a fixed mindset since they
know that there's nothing they can do
about their talent or ability and they
know that the only way you can determine
whether somebody has it or not is by
looking at their performance they want
their performance to always look good so
their goal in life is to look good and
that will convey the message that they
must have it
they must be intelligent or talented so
that becomes the primary driver for
everything is I want to look good for
someone with the agile mindset or the
growth mindset it's about learning
so the goal is get better the goal is
strive work hard improve so they had the
setting of the goal would be rather to
try and or to set a goal I might not be
able to reach but indeed trying to reach
it I will learn something I want to be
better at so that means that if I'm a
musician for instance I really want to
take a hard course or I want to study
with a difficult teacher because now in
those situations I have a chance of
getting better I have a chance of
learning whereas if I had the fixed
mindset and I were a musician well I
might not be so interested in that I
would want to be in a situation where I
might be the best player in the group I
might be the one who looks good
so I look for situations where I'm going
to have the appearance of having the
talent or the ability and probably not
going to learn much at all um is it that
people have a like a complete mindset so
other people which have the fixed
mindset don't people who have the gross
mindset or the edgehog mindset or is it
more mixed we're all a mixture we're all
a mixture but we also all tend to lean
in one direction or another and I always
use myself as an example because I think
for the most part I'm an agile mindset
holder but I know that I have little
areas where I can see it in myself and
what you look for are those things that
you tell yourself what what is the
little voice in your head saying to you
about that particular area so for me and
I've been working on this so I'm trying
to get better its artistic talent I
can't draw and see that's just the way I
said that I can't I can't do that so
whatever you find yourself saying that
phrase to yourself I can't do that
that's fixed mindset or I've never been
able to that's fix mine
and what Carol Dweck suggests is that
you say well I can't do that yet
that's agile and if you have that little
voice in your hand that's saying
something to you about an area where you
would like to be better try saying that
to yourself instead of the little voice
saying I can't draw say I can't draw yet
but you can still decide that you don't
want to develop that skill yes you can
you can and in fact you can be your own
worst enemy if you can argue with
yourself and you can say no no I can't
draw I know I can't draw I've never been
able to draw then really that low voice
is not your voice it's probably a
teacher a parent maybe a grandparent who
told you over and over you can't do that
you're not the artist or the musician or
you you could never be something that's
that didn't come from you that came from
some some mentor or somebody who
influenced you when you were a young
child and now you have that in your head
and you think that's you really it's
someone else and you can change that you
can make that your voice and you can
make that more agile so everyone can
start learning to draw yes absolutely
so I have now a lot of books because
since I said that I've been asked that
question many times since I have said
that now I have lots of friends and they
have sent me books and I even have one
friend who made a video for me how to
start and to draw circles and make faces
and then it can make animals and other
kinds of artifacts starting with a
circle so I can do that now I I will
never be wonderful but I'm better than I
was and so I know that I'm improving but
you still have the fixed months it kind
of
a little bit yeah a little bit although
you have proved to yourself that I can I
can do it I can do it it's it's it's
more difficult than it seems
so I have a lot of sympathy for people
who can get stuck and I know they're
doing it to themselves but I can see
that I do that to myself
as well it's not a trivial exercise
let's maybe go a little bit into the
discussion so we know now you have a
fixed mindsets for or you you tend to
have a fixed mindset for drawing you
probably don't have a fixed mindsets for
stuff like public speaking or no
learning style I brought the brain yes
well and oh and what might be the
biggest fear of all for people who are
my age is to not be afraid to come to a
conference like this where everyone here
is much younger than 73 and to feel that
not only can I get up on stage and talk
which is a fearful thing for a lot of
people in itself but to think that I
might have something interesting to say
to people who are so much younger and
who are very busy who are taking time
out of their lives to listen to me
that's I think shows a lot of courage I
hope I will do it as well I can't
promise you I will try to be better I
can't promise you if I will be better
but if I want to self-assess myself how
could I detect if I have the fixed
mindset or the anjaan mindset listen for
those voices listen for those voices and
how do you describe other people and if
you find yourself labeling other people
to say oh well obviously they they are
talented they have it that's fixed and I
don't
hmm that's the fixed mindset so you
listen for the words that you use and if
you start saying especially if the
pronouns are well he can do it I can't
do that or he's the wizard on the team
he's the one who can always find the
difficult bug or we always ask Joe to do
the architecture he's such a talented
architecture those are fixed mindset
observations and what you're saying is
well Joe has it I don't and that means
that you're labeling people who's got it
and as soon as you start doing that that
means you stereotype and if somebody has
it that means somebody else doesn't have
it and now you put them both in a box
and you've said oh well we wouldn't ever
ask him for advice on the architecture
because he doesn't have it and now we've
said he can't learn he can't be better
he can't contribute where's Joe has all
of the talent and all of the ability
that can destroy a team faster than
anything I know of is to start labeling
people than to say who has it and who
doesn't because now we discount the
contributions of a lot of people well
maybe they don't have it now but they
could they don't have it yet they could
be better they could contribute so
labeling people is exactly what
companies do to destroy lives
it's what teams do to destroy lives we
do that to each other we make our lives
smaller sometimes we do those to people
we love like our children
oh well Jimmy is the one who's the
scientist and Susie while she's the
musician and we started labeling
children at a very early age putting
them in a little box and now we're
becoming the voices that they'll hear
years later as an adult to say oh well I
can't do that and it's not their voice
at all it's
someone else who told them that over and
over yeah um so until now you have
always outlined the the negative
examples for creating a fixed mindset
life you can't do that
yes as I understand it it's also that if
I pray someone like you're so talented I
creates the fixed mindset was the answer
so the research by Carol Dweck's shows
very clearly that children who are
always told oh you're so smart oh you're
so talented oh you can do anything those
children become fixed super fixed in
fact it's beyond fixed they become
entitled they expect everyone to say oh
you're so smart not just the parents but
also all their teachers they only want
to get an A plus plus plus they only
want to do perfect work they only want
things to be absolutely right they never
want to make a mistake
they never want to fail they never want
to come in second place so they have to
get the blue ribbon they have to win the
gold cup they have to get the shining
star and that's the same thing which
happens to architects for core wizards
ah yes exactly so they become fixed as
well and once they have an extremely
fixed mindset then remember that changes
everything it changes the kinds of goals
they have is how they view work they
think work is bad I should just
naturally be able to do this it should
be easy for me I've recently watched a
documentary by Stephen Hawking and he
said when he was a student at Oxford he
never worked because they all thought if
you work that's an indication that you
don't have it so it was a badge of honor
to say oh no I didn't study for this
exam I didn't spend any time working on
these problems for physics no I I don't
need to do that
I just wrote down the answers and so
work or striving or putting it out ever
becomes a sign to the rest of the world
that you don't have it and so he said he
never worked
it wasn't till he got to Cambridge and
he started on his PhD and he had to work
that he realized what he'd been doing to
himself and said work is fun that's all
he does now so very smart people can get
into a situation where they are praised
extensively by well-meaning people who
end up creating a monster with a fixed
mindset what do I say to my coworker
when he actually did something great you
praise the effort you say as I do to my
music students you've really been
working hard on this I can see that
you've been practicing I can see that
you really worked on this particular
passage you were having trouble with
that and now you play it easily that
tells me that you must have practiced
that that you must have developed some
techniques for working past those
difficult fingerings so you praise the
effort praise the process praise the
strategy oh look at the colours in this
painting how did you decide to put blue
over here with these beautiful yellows
what was going on for you when you were
thinking about that oh I love the way
you wrote this passage how did you write
that did you decide to just write it or
did you take a break in the middle did
you walk around did you have a cup of
coffee what's your strategy for
producing words like this how to do that
and to praise how it was done not to
intimidate that it was well you're just
talented it must have been so easy for
you oh you're smart
it's a praise that praise the process
praise the process praise the effort to
praise the strategy and do the same for
your children so people you work with
wow you must have been here all weekend
working on that Wow
thank you for doing that you found that
bug yeah or you know you seem to have a
way of finding these bugs in a very fast
could you show me can you show me some
tips pairing is good for that to share
techniques so we're talking about the
technique we're talking about something
that can be learned we're talking about
something that can be improved we're not
talking about some innate ability that
you have that I could not possibly ever
emulate we're talking about something
where maybe I can't do it now but I
could learn from you you can help me be
better there is actually an interesting
study you mentioned in your talk where
they actually showed that preys and how
you deliver it makes a difference was
this children are you were ready to talk
about that so we could talk about the
research that Carol Dweck did and in it
she randomly assigned children to one
group or another and when I go through
all of the phases of the experiment I
never say how she did that assignment I
just say that she created two groups one
that had the fixed mindset and one that
had the agile or the growth mindset and
what a difference it made in their
performance on groups were probably
rendered me a sign they were random they
were totally random and they were
assigned after the first phase of the
test the first phase was an easy quiz
where all the children or this has also
been done for adults or sports teams
where everyone does really well and the
tests are graded and when they are
handing back randomly they're given to
one group of people with the praise oh
you did really well in your test you
must be very smart so the six eight
months of praising that was enough to
create the fixed mindset to the other
group is oh you did really well on your
test exactly the same you must have
worked really hard the edge on months
and that creates the edge online said
yeah so a very small we could call that
the treatment a very small treatment
creates a difference in behavior
in two groups so imagine telling a child
over and over and over day after day oh
you're so smart you're so smart you're
so smart you're so smart if in the
beginning of this experiment it can have
profound results just saying that once
what must it be like to do that to a
child every day and what were the
results actually the results of the test
showed that those children who were in
the agile mindset group when asked well
what would you like to do now do you
want to take a really hard test or you
might not do very well but you could
probably learn a lot almost all of them
90% said yes yes I'd like to take that
difficult test were those children who
were in the fixed mindset group said no
I don't think so I don't think I want to
take a hard test because they know they
wouldn't look good so over 80% of those
children said no and then when they were
asked to maybe imagine talking to a
child in the future to say you know
you're gonna do these same tests and
here's some advice those who are in the
agile mindset group said well you have
to work really hard but if you don't
understand something ask for help ask
for an explanation take your time don't
rush you can do a very good job just by
slowing down and really thinking and
working hard whereas those in the fixed
mindset said well this is a hard test
you're probably not gonna do very well
that's just the way it is and when asked
to share their test scores and this is a
common very common behavior people who
are in the fixed mindset group they lie
they will lie about their performance so
the children who are in the fixed
mindset group lied about their test
scores and they said they were higher
than they were they wanted them they
wanted to look good to conclude this a
little bit I have the impression did the
fixed mindset seems to be like the loser
on this story well we could I think we
can even say more than that we could
talk about truth
what's the truth because this is not an
opinion it's the truth that the growth
mindset or the agile mindset reflects
the real behavior of the brain because
we know yes of course people are born
with different abilities but now that we
have all this wonderful technology and
all this wonderful research and
cognitive neuroscience we can see that
when you learn how to do something it
changes your brain that if you study
music for instance you can see
violinists the parts of their brain that
operate the left hand have grown
stronger because they have to move up
and down the violin and the right hand
is stronger in different areas because
it has to work the bow so we know that
what you do your behavior does change
your brain and that as you get older you
don't fall apart if you like your
wonderful grandmother if you continue to
learn you can see it you can see
increased connectivity in your brain you
can see that your brain in some areas
can actually grow in size so that's the
truth the truth is that yes you're
limited by what you have when you're
born but everyone can always get better
that's the truth I have to I have to add
the fact to my grandmother because
listeners won't know my grandma's that
just send me the first email from a pet
so he wasn't able to do that to do any
emails before she sent me the first
email literally a few weeks after her
not his birthday that's wonderful yeah I
love it
and that's true it's the truth that just
because you're 90 that doesn't mean that
your brain has to deteriorate I have a
good friend who lives in my neighborhood
who just had a stroke and when he had a
stroke he lost the ability to speak now
if this had been 20 years ago that would
have been the end of it they would have
said oh poor man he's had a stroke now
he can't speak well that's just the way
it is very fixed mindset but not now now
they know even someone who's had a
stroke where parts of their brain have
died because a blood clot has lodged in
their brain even those brains can get
better he had the stroke in January and
at the end of three weeks he was
speaking again so by working at
improving the parts of his brain that
were not damaged
he can then rewire connections so he can
speak he can now swallow he can stand up
he can move
yes he has a walker but he's getting
stronger every day whereas you think it
wasn't that long ago when they would
have just left him to sit in a corner
until he died and how sad to think that
not only for people who have had strokes
but for the rest of us to say never give
up on your brain or your abilities that
you can always grow and you can always
improve no matter what challenges you
may face whether it's an illness or just
aging or being discouraged in a job that
as long as you're willing to work on it
and put effort into it you can always
get better that's the truth so as I
understand it the amount of fixed
mindset people versus or fixed mindset
tended to people to at John miles
attended people around fifty fifty you
would say you know I don't know whether
anybody's looked at populations like
that to say
but certainly one thing we know is that
everybody has bows there aren't any
people who are all fixed or all agile
and that we sort of shift around over
the course of our lives
and that in the beginning we are all
agile and then as we get older somehow
teachers parents can move us more in the
one direction or another and that we can
lose it so maybe two sec we're already
into the second part of this interviews
is there any proof for mine sense well
I'm trying to think of we can we can
certainly look at behavior we know that
people have different behaviors and one
of the studies long terms longitudinal
studies so by that I mean studies that
last for years and years that follow
people maybe until they die has looked
at child prodigies so a child prodigy is
someone who's born with an enormous
talent could be in anything could be
music it could be sports Tiger Woods was
a child prodigy and those children are
typically told from the very beginning
oh you're so talented or you're so smart
or you have it so the research on child
prodigies shows that most of them don't
ever do anything they drop out they
never even finish ordinary high school
they are so fixed they've been put in a
box by all of the people around them and
these enormous expectations that you're
going to be a champion tennis player or
a champion violin player or whatever it
is that they never do anything so when
you look at people who do succeed like
Tiger Woods that's not what his parents
told him they said hey you can get you
know your swing needs some work get out
there
work it was about work it was about
effort and so the study on child
prodigies who ought to all be successful
because they're also they are born with
exceptional abilities and to see that
most of them never do anything they
never do anything same conclusion if you
have a talent you should develop it yes
why is it's not worth it you can't you
can't just say oh I was born with this
therefore I don't have to do anything I
was born with it so I don't have to work
hard what Stephen Hawking told himself
he was obviously a prodigy was a genius
and for a long time he didn't do
anything and it couldn't be that if he
hadn't had his illness which really is
the thing that turned him around maybe
he never would have but suddenly he
realized I'm going to die he was given
his diagnosis of ALS pretty early in
life and they said you're going to die
in two years and he had some things that
he thought he wanted to do and he
thought I better get started and so he
he realized he had to work so if he
didn't have I would call that a wake-up
call if you don't have a wake-up call so
that's evidence I think for fixed
mindset and how destructive it can be
that even among the very talented if you
believe you don't have to do anything
you never achieve any success at all all
right so let's switch topic at this
point this morning you talked about
experiments scientific experiments why
are scientific experiments important we
don't have any proof for anything we do
in software I've been in this field long
enough so that agile is just it's the
latest thing it's not the answer I can
remember when I can remember when there
wasn't any design there was no design
bathe no design at all it was just a lot
of assembler code and it was you know I
don't know if you ever seen one of the
printouts from a machine where you know
goes on for miles and so when you're
trying to find something you've got a
big stack of paper
that and there's no way of finding your
way around in it so you say okay I think
the problem is here so you put your
finger at that point and then okay then
few pages okay it says go to and I'm
better fine now put this finger in here
and you have to keep track there's no
structure to it
yeah there's no module no labeling it's
just a bunch of go twos that tied
together assembler instructions so
there's no design and then design
appeared and we said wouldn't it be
better if we had a programming language
to support this where we could say well
you know here's a sort of a piece of the
program why do we say that that does
this and we'll call it something and
there was wow this is revolutionary it's
gonna change everything well it did it
did but it didn't solve all our problems
and then then we need structured things
so we had all the structured approaches
we in structure and design structured
analysis everything's programmers
oh isn't this wonderful all this will
make our lives so much easier and well
it did but it was just an evolutionary
step and for every point along the way
everyone agreed yes things are getting
better
yes we think that this is the right way
to go but do we have any proof for this
no it was just a lot of stories that
people said yeah you know it does make
sense instead of having to put all your
fingers into the side of the printout
yeah it would be better to be able to
call that module and to say alright I
can call another module yeah now the
pieces are a little easier to understand
and this long stream of assembler code
yeah that's common sense common sense
but that's all we have we have no
scientific proof we never do experiments
we never compare the behavior of two
teams randomly assigned we never
do that it's not a scientific discipline
at all it's not a science
it's not it's not even engineering
really because engineering would be
based on a science and what's the
science that we could say there's
computer science and software
engineering but that's not it's not true
software engineering is not an
engineering discipline and it doesn't
rest on a science computer science we
just used the name science was common
sense not enough it's the story I told
this morning I get that all the time
well it was just common sense Linda it's
just common sense and the story that
from this morning's talk was about using
leeches that doctors used leeches on
human beings for over 2,000 years it was
just common sense because we know that
you're sick because you have too much of
one kind of humor or another black bile
yellow bile so if we bleed you then that
will give your body a chance to adjust
and now you won't be out of balance
anymore and you'll get better well
that's just common sense isn't it seems
like yeah so we have a lot of behaviors
not only using leeches but other things
that we do that are common sense and are
never questioned just because everybody
does it that doesn't mean that it's the
right thing to do it's just common
practice so that's what we have we have
a bunch of common practices and we move
from one set of common practices to
another and we say all along let's just
make sense it's just common sense when
really if we did some randomized control
trials RCTs we could see for ourselves
we're even in agile develop more still
arguing about some things that we have
argued valdek aids should we do some
kind of code inspection as well or is
the testing enough what wouldn't
randomized controlled trial for code
inspection to play you'd have to have
two equivalent teams randomly assigned
we never do that if we ever do any kind
of protists
typing or proof-of-concept
we handpick those people we never just
say well okay it looks like fred is
gonna be on that team okay Joe is going
to we never do that we hand-picked those
people that's why prototypes are or
experiments that we could call there
they're not really experiments they're
people who want to be on I'll pick me I
want to be on that team too so it would
be randomized and they would be
equivalent this team is equivalent to
this team and we randomly assigned
people and now we would have the same
project and we would have everything
else the same except for the one
variable we're trying to tease out and
then we would have some way of measuring
and what would that be
we're not even very good at MIT I
remember when I was talking about design
patterns then a manager came in and he
said Linda I said we start doing design
patterns will we be better and I said
Wow how good are you now on a scale of
one to ten are you a three or are you
attend how good are you no so even if we
did the experiment how would we measure
when we got to the end what would we
measure would we measure bugs lines of
code usability user friendliness
customer satisfaction I don't know we'd
have to have a concrete objective
measure to say clearly in this version
of the experiment this practice is
better than that practice and that would
only be the first iteration because all
experiments if you go to science physics
chemistry psychology it can't just be
one pass it's got to be repeatable you
have to publish their results and then
someone else must read it and say
all right I will try to duplicate that
and see if I can verify your results so
we we don't have the resources to do it
once let alone hope that other
organizations would duplicate that and
do their own randomized trials hmm what
is their way to introduce that into the
industry because I apparently no one is
doing I think the way we're doing it now
is a pretty good way because what I've
done with retrospectives is to say to my
teams you know we're not gonna really go
back and do five whys and dig off all
the problems you had listened to that
let's instead say there's some
interesting things that maybe we could
experiment with and let's do that over
the next iteration and it will be a very
short trial this is not gonna be
randomized and we're the only ones who
are going to be involved in this but
we've been talking about doing something
interesting so here's an example
concrete example so I talked a lot about
sitting we sit too much it's really bad
for your brain you don't do as well
sitting it would be better if you stood
up and moved around a little bit so now
people are making standing desks or
treadmill desks or but those are so
expensive so I talk about it all the
time and have a lot of teams who say wow
we would like to try that but we don't
have any money we can't buy a $500
standing desk or a truck we just can't
do it and even if our manager could come
up with the money you would say well how
do I know that we're gonna spend $500
and you'll really use it and maybe if we
had an experiment we could try it how
would you design such an experiment so I
said how would you design such an
experiment
and they said okay alright here's what
we'll do we will get some boxes we will
get some cardboard boxes and we will put
them up full make varying Heights on our
desks and we can just pick up our
laptops and we will put them on the
boxes and we will try standing for a
certain amount of time every day and so
everybody decided to do it in a slightly
different way because there are
different heights people are different
heights so they had to make their own
boxes and we sell care for the next two
weeks we're all gonna try to stand a
certain number of hours every day and
we're going to see at the end of two
weeks we had no idea what we would even
measure so we'll be purely subjective as
we will just ask in our retrospective
well how was that for you how is how was
standing how many hours did you stand
what did you feel at the end of every
day and what's your evaluation and it's
what we found and every team I've done
that I've done that with several teams
now is that they liked it they said I
feel better I noticed that after lunch
when I would always be so sleepy and I
would have to go have lots of coffee
that now instead I stand up so they had
an objective measure they were buying
less coffee
they had another objective measure some
of them had a lot of even young people
have back pain or different kinds of
other shoulder pain and they said when I
stand up I don't have that so I'm not
taking tylenol or a leave or medication
for the back pain said I I really don't
have it or it's so diminished that I
don't really need it so he really did
have some objective measures fewer cups
of coffee
fewer Tylenol ingestion and subjective
measure but they felt better you see a
few matters this measurements before you
know we didn't know we we we know just
noticed afterwards because in the
beginning we had no idea what was going
to happen
and that will be that's kind of like a
magic thing that if you just set up the
idea of an experiment and you say we
don't really know what what we're gonna
measure that they will emerge in many
cases there'll be things that can that
will come about so in another little
experiment we did is that the the people
who are in charge of facilities would
not move our desks in Germany someone
would argue that it's illegal to have
yes working on boxes that's right yes
yes I can I can see that so this is a
similar kind of thing and we said we
really would like we're not sitting
close together and it's so difficult
because you know like Joe is over an
anion so we did a little shuffling of
desks around and we didn't know what we
were going to measure but we said we'll
try this for the next iteration and we
hope that we don't get into trouble
doing what we did we found ways of doing
that we didn't actually move any
furniture we just borrowed things we
borrow things and at the end of the
iteration I said well I just was looking
for subjectivity and so how was that for
you and he said I know that this was
more effective because it always used to
take me a certain amount of time because
I had to go all the way over to where
Joe is and I usually went over they
actually tracked it I usually go over
and see him two or three times a day it
takes me a certain number of minutes to
get over there he was always busy around
the phone so I had to wait so there's
enough more time wasted when he's right
here I can see and we snot on the phoned
and I say hey Joe I need to talk to you
about said so you know three trips we're
at each one took me 20 minutes that's an
hour a day I saved an hour a day for two
weeks but isn't that common sense not
necessarily it is common sense that's
true but we were able to actually
measure it so now we can go to the
manager and we can say you know we made
these cardboard boxes and yes we know
standing down
sar expensive but what we notice is not
as much coffee was bought we're not
taking as many drugs that's got to make
an improvement in the quality of the
things that we were working on and he
bought it
managers like numbers and if you can
give them any positive incentive to say
you know you could make things better
for us if you bought us some standing
desks and we did a little experiment and
we can show that yeah there were some
measurable benefits most managers are
intelligent people who want you to do a
good job and if they can possibly see a
way to do that they'll do it so we can
argue the time for the other one say we
saved an hour a day in communication
overhead by just having Joe here instead
of having them on the other side of the
building
couldn't we move Joe permanently
couldn't we do that yeah I bet we could
how do you start getting the team into
an experiment mindset because when I go
into a retrospective oftentimes I have
the the feeling people people always
propose an action item and immediately
take it up but never see it as an
experiment well I mean you could call it
an action item if you want it but my
experience is that they think it's fun
retrospectives can be retrospectives can
be boring you know I get that a lot
well here we are again it's the same
thing what worked well and then we never
get anything done the action items
sometimes we do and sometimes we don't
do them but experiments Wow and along
with that is I call the real time
timeline so instead of waiting to the
retrospective to do the timeline we do
it as it happens and when the timeline
goes up as it happens often I tell them
that they should be reading what goes up
and they should send that over to their
unconscious mind and let the unconscious
come up with some ideas for experiments
and so there this is continuous retro
space
not just waiting until the end and it's
also taking advantage of the power of
the unconscious mind which can come up
with all kinds of wonderful ideas
instead of sitting consciously in a room
saying we have an hour to come up with
some action items and we know how slow
and deliberate and what's that's another
way of putting it deliberate that
conscious mind is it's just it can't
it's so limited we need to hand more
over to the unconscious mind and this is
a way of doing it so if they know that's
the way things are gonna be done then as
they're building the timeline they're
thinking hmm maybe we could think of a
way I'll sleep on it and then let it go
and then a couple of days later I've got
it why don't we try so it's a different
mindset if you will the mindset of
saying we should always be looking for
little tiny things to do better way
don't have time for big major major
upheavals are just some little tiny
things then maybe like the standing desk
how you don't know how to do that but
somebody else on the team might say oh
I've got an idea I've got some boxes in
my garage and I can bring those in and
we can cut them up and we can try to so
it's fun it's a fun thing if I and want
to try studying is that what the first
step the first step would be to say
we're gonna do real-time timeline now
instead of waiting until the end and
then as we build a timeline we're gonna
constantly so this is continuous we
should all be moving toward flow anyway
continuous we should be thinking of
ideas not wait until the end of the week
or the two weeks and say alright now is
the time to think about it no we should
think about it all the time and that's
easy for us to do because the
unconscious mind is sitting there
available to us all the time it never
sleeps and it can come up with
most amazing creative things and it can
multitask the unconscious can think
about a million things all at the same
time so giving it one more thing it's
nothing no burden at all
it's the conscious mind that's limited
so you need to think of more ways to
offload the conscious deliberate linear
slow processor and move it over to the
fast multitasking room full of smart
people that you carry around with you
and this is a good way to do that and
then prepare to be surprised because we
work with amazing people who are
creative on all they need is a key how
do i how do i unlock that door and you
say it's with an experiment well we have
to talk about the release game so the
the game is called release in all
capital letters with an exclamation
point and it's a fun game for software
developers and in it are a whole host of
agile figures and I'm one of them so
I've never been in a game before so it's
kind of exciting so just Google on
release exclamation point and up will
come these amazing decks of cards and I
can tell you yes you can go buy them but
this wonderful company has also made
available free pdf so you can print out
your own cards and cut them up and make
your own deck if you want to so then so
go out and buy the release game and now
we have a new fearless change book it
took us ten years to write fearless
change and it's been 10 years so it has
taken us another 10 to write more
fearless change so we seem to work in 10
EUR increments 10 years so put this
little piece out there ten years for the
next it's called more fearless change it
has 15 new patterns and what we call
insights into the old patterns or the
original patterns so that we can tell
you
what we've learned over the last ten
years of using those patterns so it's
now out it's now available I just gave
away my first free copy at the
conference today I'm definitely gonna
read that where can our listeners find
out more about the brain the stuff
you're you're doing and oh we've been
talking about podcasts yes
so I love podcasts I I do read I read
real print magazines and real print
books and I also have things on my
Kindle but my primary source of
information for just about anything is
podcasts so my favorite all-time brain
podcast is called brain science podcast
and it is a little technical it's pretty
heavy-duty the moderator is a physician
and so she can speak to medical terms
and typically what she does is interview
the author of a book about neuroscience
so you can listen for typically an hour
and you can hear whether the book is
something you'd like to read on your own
or not so it's a good guide into the
current literature so I recommend it
highly I also like to listen to radio
lab just because they cover such a wide
variety of topics and it's so well done
the same thing is true for Freakonomics
another one of my favorites well done
and interesting and just completely
entertaining Scientific American
publishes several podcasts they're all
one minute 60 seconds that's challenge
60 seconds so there's one non-silent
just science
so it's called 60 second science and
again you get to hear a little snippet
about some scientific finding and if you
want to follow up on that then you can
read the paper otherwise it's
interesting information there's one
called 60 second mind and it's about
cognitive neuroscience and again you
hear about some interesting finding or
you say I'm not
interested in that and I I can ignore it
there's also an interesting podcast
called 99 you and you mano Yamano
technical you mano history and yeah I
just I spend a lot of time listening to
podcasts well in software engineering
radio I guess I guess no that I guess
ladies so how can people find out more
about you well you can go to my website
Linda rising dot org and I try to keep
it up to date but I don't always succeed
or what I find is a good way to see what
I'm doing is just Google on Linda rising
and almost all conferences now are
videotaping presentations so all the
presentations that I have given are out
there and they seem to be freely
accessible and I I think it's a good
thing to go to conferences yes but there
are so many conferences info queue has
an enormous amount of information a lot
of talks there that have been recorded
so we have a wealth of information don't
we we're lucky yes and to all the things
that you mentioned we will prepare show
notes so people don't have to dig it out
great okay and I would say thank you
very much for being specially measure we
always like to have you here thank you I
I would like to mention that we are
looking what you listeners think of this
episode and the other episode so go to
se test ratio dotnet and leave a comment
you can use the email address team at
SEO dotnet we are at su radio on Twitter
and we are software engineering radio on
LinkedIn Google+ and Facebook so that's
for me to say thanks for listening this
is your handles for software engineering
video goodbye
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or read review on itunes mention
a message us on Twitter at se radio or
search for the software engineering
radio group on LinkedIn Google+ or
Facebook you can also email us at team @
SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
the creative commons two-point-five
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]